In this interview, I'm going to be
talking to energy economist Aaron Cosby
about an act that is being considered in
the American Congress that could have
very considerable implications for the
Canadian economy. We reported on it when
it was first announced last fall and
Aaron's going to give us an update. So,
welcome to the interview, Aaron.
>> Very good to be here. Look, this is
fascinating because you know the uh the
Europe has had its border carbon
adjustment mechanism for about 21 h
sorry 2021. So uh emissions intensity
gets uh taxed on imports. China is
coming out is extending its uh uh car
industrial emitters carbon tax uh over
the next few few years. We never thought
we'd see one in the United States, but
in fact, there is a sort of, you know,
that kind of a bill in front of the
Congress, is there not?
>> There is. Uh, it's it was introduced in
the last Congress and and didn't pass,
but that's typical for these kinds of
bills. Has been reintroduced in a
revised form in this Congress, and it it
would levy a charge at the border based
on the carbon contained in imported
goods.
>> Tell uh what is the name of the act?
It's the foreign pollution fee act and
it was introduced by Republican uh
senator uh Bill Cassidy.
>> And this is interesting because uh last
fall uh economist Chris Patai who you
know uh was in the room when John
Podesta uh announced it now that this
was kind of a Biden
initiative. Uh but this one's got it's
introduced by Republicans and and seems
to have bipartisan support. Right.
>> That's right. So the the the thing that
Podesta announced was a trade and
climate change task force. So we knew
that this the the link between trade and
climate change was on the political
radar uh of the Democrats and it always
has been. You know, for the last 10
years, we've had bills stacked up in
Congress, you know, three or four at a
time that have proposed some kind of US
carbon price and a border carbon
adjustment uh to to balance that out, to
level the playing field with foreign
importers. This one is different. It was
proposed for for two reasons. One, it
was proposed by Republicans. There's
three Republican sponsors for this bill.
So, it's not a Democratic initiative. Uh
and it it it plays to the bipartisan
objective of trying to ring fence China,
right? Basically, uh the second
difference is this one does not contain
any kind of a proposal for a US carbon
price. It imposes a price at the border
uh on foreign uh uh carbon, but it
doesn't propose a US carbon price. And
for both of those reasons, this one is
far more likely to actually end up in
law than than any of the previous
iterations.
>> Uh let's start with China. Um why would
the US target in this way?
>> The US is searching uh in any way it can
to protect domestic industries like
steel and aluminum. um that are under
pressure from Chinese over supply
um and and under pressure basically
because of a years decades of lack of
investment. They they've been hidden
behind tariff walls for for a number of
years. So they haven't made the kind of
modernizing investment that makes them
globally competitive. So the US needs
some way to shore up support in these
sectors. They're also very politically
important sectors because they sit in
swing states. Um, so we're looking for
ways to uh combat all to to address all
of those problems and a bill that can
protect clean American production versus
dirty Chinese production fits the fits
the bill very nicely. It ticks a lot of
boxes.
>> Yeah, this seems to be the kind of bill
that let's say that it passed both
houses and then went on to uh President
Trump's desk for for a signature. Um,
it's not a tariff, but it kind of acts
in the same way as a tariff does, and
it's something that he might support.
>> It feels like a tariff.
Technically, it's not a tariff, but it
feels like a tariff. And and therefore,
yes, I think this is likely to resonate
with this current administration, which
is so fixed on border charges. Of
course, you know, it's it's hard to
predict what resonates with this
administration. We're in a dynamic
period of of policy uncertainty, but you
know, if anything is going to resonate,
this kind of thing would
>> um where are we at with this uh act and
when are we likely to see it come to a
vote?
>> So, again, it's been reintroduced into
the current sitting Congress, the 119th
Congress. Um, and it's it's, you know,
the way these things work, it's it's
under a lobbying effort by the
proponents who are trying to find enough
bipartisan support to bring the bill to
the floor. Um, and they're engaged in
that. Now, the problem is there's so
much else going on, it's it's hard to
capture the attention of lawmakers, but
uh I think we're likely to see well,
their objective is to bring it to a vote
within this Congress. So that would be
in the next uh year or so, year or two.
Um and and it's it's anybody's guess
whether that's a poss whether that's
going to happen, but that's certainly
their objective.
>> Now what are the implications for Canada
and in the energy field? Uh you know the
we Canada currently and well Alberta uh
exports 3.2 2 3.3 million barrels per
day of vitamin which has a very very
high uh emissions intensity. Uh it
averages 66 kilograms of CO2 equivalent
per barrel compared to 31 kg of CO2E
which is the American average. So one
would think that that the uh Alberta oil
exports would be caught by this tax were
it implemented.
>> Yes. So I mean the first version of this
bill did contain did cover uh energy
exports like uh crude from Canada and
would have caught Canadian producers in
the way that you described. The version
that's currently circulating doesn't
cover oil exports, doesn't cover crude
exports. Um that's not to say it never
would because the the criteria for
inclusion of new sectors are is a little
fuzzy and not not objective in the way
that you would you would have wanted. Uh
so it's easy to imagine that this bill
ultimately could do just what you
described. It could catch up Canadian
oil production and assign that that a
carbon tax based on and and it's
important average Canadian GHG
intensity. This bill doesn't focus on
individual producer performance. It
focuses on national averages. Uh and
that would be a bad thing for Canada for
the reason you you you've explained.